Rajeev Jain

Principal Research Software Specialist · Argonne National Laboratory Chicago · Mathematics and Computer Science

★ rajeeja.github.io □ rajeeja@gmail.com □ +1 312-725-3380 in linkedin □ google scholar □ github

Summary

2007 - 2009

I have 14 years of experience managing/developing software projects and two masters degree: one in computer science and other in structural enginneering. I like to learn new things, I am familiar with several programming languages and tools used to execute complex projects.

WORK EXPERIENCE

2018 – 2022 Principal Research Software Specialist, Mathematics and Computer Science Argonne National Laboratory

- ⇒ Managed junior developers and completed software projects from conceptualization to actual coding.
- ⇒ Significantly reduced the time taken by domain scientists to launch and analyze large runs on super-computers.
- ⇒ Used our hyperparameter optimization on COVID-19 deep neural network (DNN) models and delivered improved results. Scripted big runs on HPC clusters.
- ⇒ Wrote reports and published papers in peer-reviewed journals and conferences such as the supercomputing conference.

2011 – 2018 Software Development Specialist, Mathematics and Computer Science Argonne National Laboratory

- ⇒ Handled the coupled urban exascale simulation project, lead a diverse team of experts from different national labs and universities.
- ⇒ My reactor generator tool was used by Kitware Inc. to write and get SBIR funding Phase 1 for \$225k and Phase 2 for \$750k for a 2 year period. They developed GUI and added some new features to the toolset.
- ⇒ Greatly improved the runtime and memory utilization of simulation codes by using distributed computing techniques and libraries.
- ⇒ Lead the developer of MeshKit, presented yearly updates to U.S. scientific funding agencies in the Washington D.C. office.

2009 – 2011 Pre-doctoral Appointee, Mathematics and Computer Science Argonne National Laboratory

⇒ Gathered requirements and developed the scalable reactor geometry and mesh generation tool using C++.

Research and Teaching Assistant, Civil Engineering in the School of Sustainable Engineering and the Built
Environment

ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY

- ⇒ Mentored students to solve structural engineering problems and graded assignements.
- ⇒ Wrote multidisciplinary, scalable code for running simulation jobs in distributed systems.

2006 – 2007 **Project Engineer**, SAP/Java Wipro Technologies, Bangalore/Hyderabad, India

- ⇒ Complete Java programming course and worked on a mobile payment systems for Nokia (Bangalore)
- ⇒ 3 months training in SAP ABAP and started working in a project with Kodak (Hyderabad)

Summer 2005 Research Trainee, Engineering Research Division TATA MOTORS, PUNE, INDIA

 \Rightarrow Performed hot and cold circuit automobile engine fitted with retarder.

SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT PROJECTS

2020 – present Co-Developer, UXarray GITHUB LINK

Helped design and code the first draft of the UXARRAY API, wrote python functions to integrate and read/write unstructured grids.

2016 – present Co-Developer, ECP-CANDLE GITHUB LINK

Published papers on model robustness with counterfactuals / noise injection and hyper-parameter optimization framework "Supervisor". Currently focussed on testing claims made by the recent artificial inteligence (AI-based) cancer drug-response papers, creating a framework for understanding model sensitivity and XAI

2018 – present Co-Developer, Flash-X

DOCUMENTATION

Designed/coded asynchronous write and compression of HDF5 checkpoint file. Help with performance benchmarking on DOE supercomputers, CI, documentation. Review/manage GitHub policies, actions, PRs, issues etc.

2009 – 2016 Lead Developer, MeshKit

BITBUCKET LINK

Principal Investigator for MeshKit (mesh generation C++ toolkit) for the reactor geometry generation package (RGG). Wrote several mesh/geometry generation algorithms and published in peer-reviewed conferences/journals.

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- R. Jain, A. Shah. J. Mohd-Yusof. et al. "Probing Decision Boundaries in Cancer Data Using Noise Injection and Counterfactual Analysis." (2021)
- 2. **R. Jain**, K. Weide. S. Chawdhary. T. Klostermann. "Checkpoint/Restart for Lagrangian particle mesh with AMR in community code FLASH-X." *arXiv preprint arXiv:2103.04267* (2021)
- 3. **R. Jain**, X. Luo. G. Sever. T. Hong. C. Catlett. "Representation and evolution of urban weather boundary conditions in downtown Chicago." *Journal of Building Performance Simulation* 13, 182–194 (2020)
- 4. J. M. Wozniak. **R. Jain**, P. Balaprakash. et al. "Candle/supervisor: A workflow framework for machine learning applied to cancer research." *BMC bioinformatics* 19, 59–69 (2018)
- 5. P. O'Leary. J. Becker. R. O'Bara. D. Thompson. **R. Jain**, et al. "Providing a Graphical Tool for Modeling Reactor Cores." *Transactions of the American Nuclear Society* 118, (2018)
- 6. **R. Jain**, T. J. Tautges. "PostBL: Post-mesh boundary layer mesh generation tool." *Proceedings of the 22nd International Meshing Roundtable* 331–348 (2014)
- 7. T. J. Tautges. R. Jain, "Creating geometry and mesh models for nuclear reactor core geometries using a lattice hierarchy-based approach." *Engineering with Computers* 28, 319–329 (2012)
- 8. R. Jain, "Blast Mitigation solutions via FEM-Based Design Optimization." (2009)

Honors

2010 – present	Mentor, Supervised several summer students/postdocs a	and staff members	Argonne National Laboratory
	NUMGRID 2020 Invited: Program Committee Member, Managed and reviewed papers		
2015	Reviewer and Session Chair	Computational Geo	DMETRIES, SNA AND MC CONFERENCE
2015-2017	Advisor and developer Commercialization of RGG, clic	k for details Kı	tware Inc. for SBIR Phase I and II
2011	Co-chair Argonne/C	SUI Undergraduat	te/Graduate Research Symposium.
2007 - 2009	University Graduate Fellowship, \$4000	Arizona State University	
2004 - 2004	ıst Prize for Low Budget Car Design Contest, INR 40k-	TECH FEST IIT I	KHARAGPUR AND MINDA LTD. DELHI

EDUCATION

2017 - 2020	Masters of Science Computer Science	University of Chicago
2007 - 2009	Master of Science Structural Engg. (Minor Computer Science)	Arizona State University
	Thesis title: "Blast Mitigation solutions via FEM-Based Design Optimization."	
2002 – 2006	B.Tech Mechanical Engineering	IIT Dhanbad, India

OTHER SKILLS AND ACTIVITIES

2012-present	Mentor School kids with STEM Mentoring Cafe	
2011-2017	Reviewer International Meshing Roundtable (IMR).	
2015	Reviewer SBIR (Small Business Funding Proposals)	
2015	ATPESC scholar world-class training for selected applicants on HPC and big data	
2017-present	Member Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) and American Nuclear Society (ANS).	
	Following: Cricket, Biking, Table-tennis, Crypto-currencies and International affairs.	